Guide to the Miner Searle Bates Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Miner Searle Bates Papers
1836-1979
RG 10
Yale University Divinity School Library
55
(132 boxes)
These papers document Bates' career as a missionary, academic, and author. They also include an extensive collection of information for his book on Christian effort in Chinese society from 1900 to 1950, which he was in the process of writing at the time of his death. There are over 3,000 pages of drafts for this book included in the collection. The papers include correspondence, notes, writings, and printed material related to Bates' work in Nanking, China, particularly his role in relief work during World War II. Miner Searle Bates (1897-1978) was educated at Hiram College (B.A., 1916), Oxford University (B.A., 1919; M.A., 1920), and Yale University (Ph.D., 1935). He was a missionary, professor of history at the University of Nanking, China from 1920-1950, organizing member of Nanking International Safety Zone Committee and chairman of Nanking International Relief Committee, 1939-1941, and professor of missions, Union Theological Seminary, New York, 1950-1965.
Bates, M. Searle (Miner Searle), 1897-1978
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Bates family.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Biographical / Historical
1897 May 28 Born in Newark, Ohio
1916 B.A. Hiram College, of which father, Miner Lee Bates, was President 1908-1930
1916-1917 Oxford University, Rhodes Scholar
1917-1918 Secretary for International Y.M.C.A. on war service, India and Mesopotamia
1919-1920 Oxford University; completed B.A. in Honour School of Modern History, two further terms in political science and general history for M.A.
1920 July Commissioned as missionary of United Christian Missionary Society
1920-1950 Professor of History, University of Nanking, China
1923 Married Lilliath Robbins who became tho mother of Morton Gaylord (1926) and Robert Searle (1928)
1934-1935 Rockefeller Foundation Fellow in Harvard University
1935 Ph.D., Yale University
1936-1941 Seven visits to Japan on behalf cf Christian organizations
1937-1941 Remained in Nanking when University of Nanking removed to Chengtu, West China, in charge of maintenance of University activities and properties. Organizing member, Nanking International Safety Zone Committee. Member and chairman (1939-1941) of Nanking International Relief Committee.
1950-1965 Professor of Missions, Union Theological Seminary, New York
1978 Died
For additional information see Series VIII, Box 126, Folder 1132.
Scope and Contents
I. Correspondence, 1920-1978, n.d.
II. China Notes and Sources, 1836-1978, n.d.
III. "Christian Effort in Chinese Society" Drafts
IV. Documentation of Prominent Chinese Christians
V. Other Notes and Collected Material, 1928-1978, n.d.
VI. Writings, 1924-1975, n.d.
VII. Course Related Materials, 1942-1965, n.d.
VIII. Personal Items and Memorabilia
Bates was a faithful collector of letters, reports, and writings relating to his own life and work. He was a thorough, if somewhat disorganized, scholar, familiar with nearly all available publications in his field of specialization. Being the personal records of a professional historian, the Bates Papers provide not only documentation of Bates' own career as missionary, academic and author, but also an impressive collection of information related to the history of Christianity in China.
Bates' work in China spanned the years 1920 to 1950 and included leadership roles at the University of Nanking and in relief work during World War II He was an intelligent and highly educated missionary, well equipped to observe and report on the Chinese context in which he lived. Following his return from China, Bates continued to be prominent in the field of missions as a professor at Union Seminary and author of many articles and papers. His expertise was much in demand by organizations such as the International Missionary Council, World Council of Churches, National Council of Churches, and United Board for Christian Higher Education in Asia. He was called upon to participate in many study groups and conferences.
It was no doubt the extent of these demands, added to Bates' own penchant for thoroughness, which prevented the completion of his magnum opus. At the time of his death in 1978 Bates had been striving for over fifteen years to produce a concise survey of Christian effort in Chinese society from 1900 to 1950 By 1971 he had developed "card indexes for several thousand books, pamphlets, articles seen to be of value or prospective value.. ." He had taken notes on major mission periodicals and yearbooks, on "documents of all types from China Continuation Committee 1913-1921, National Christian Council and its various units 1922-1950; about 200 biographies including Chinese; writings of a number of Chinese leaders; selected Chinese journals; histories of individual missions, organizations, institutions, many dissertations and theses, selected unpublished papers, letters and 'oral history' transcriptions". (From "Some Indicators of What Has Been Done," Series III Box 116, Folder 993.) These raw materials -bibliographic references, notes, and annotated photocopies -- comprise a major portion of this manuscript group. In many cases, the information Bates had collected is readily available elsewhere, but there is also unique and valuable material here to be found by the patient researcher. The over 3,000 pages of drafts which Bates had completed by 1978 constitute a major achievement in themselves.
Series I, Correspondence, is divided into three sections: Family Correspondence, China Era Correspondence (from the period when Bates was serving in China) and General Correspondence (primarily from the period after Bates' return from China). Of particular interest in the Family Correspondence are letters written by Bates to wife and sons during 1937 and 1938 when he was serving as an organizing member of the Nanking International Safety Zone Committee, chairman of the Nanking International Relief Committee, director of economic and social surveys, and investigator of opium and heroin traffic in Japanese-occupied territory. These letters, those in the China Era Correspondence from the same time period, and reports and memoranda found in Series II and Series VI together provide valuable detailed description of a turbulent situation.
There are additional items of interest scattered among the family letters, such as a letter from Bates to his sister regarding the mental health of a Ginling College professor. Informative circular letters written by Bates and his wife for distribution to friends and supporters are found in both the Chlna and General Correspondence sections. Letters from colleagues and students seeking Bates' counsel or assistance form a large portion of the General Correspondence. There are also letters related to various projects and institutions with which Bates was involved, including the International Missionary Council China Study Project (1954-1956), the China Records Project (1968-1973), and the Missionary Research Library at Union Theological Seminary (1951-1978).
Series II, China Notes and Sources, contains the materials which Bates had gathered in preparation for writing his survey of Christian effort in China. This large mass of bibliographic references, handwritten and typed notes, summaries, and annotated photocopies came to the Library in a chaotic state. The materials have been organized in eight sections but since Bates often made carbon copies of notes and duplicated photocopies for distribution in different categories, some of the material may appear in more than one section. A small amount of material related to China but without direct application to Bates' projected book has been included in this Series.
A. Whenever convenient the material has been arranged according to the outline which Bates had devised, indicating time period and subject matter. In most cases only material which is clearly marked with one outline number has been included in this section. The sorting was complicated by the fact that Bates apparently was working from more than one outline; some notes are clearly marked with an outline number which does not exist in the final outline or which does not represent the same subject area. These items have been filed under the correct outline number whenever possible.
B. Bates often dictated running notes on an entire monograph, essay or thesis and then went back to indicate appropriate outline numbers in the margins of the typed copy. In other cases he photocopied sections of works and annotated the copies with outline numbers in the margins. Section B of Series II contains notes and photocopies which are applicable to more than one outline section and therefore could not be filed easily by outline number. This material has been filed by author, with titles provided for a selected list of more interesting or obscure monographs, essays or theses. Many of the sources represented in this section are widely available but others are unpublished theses, papers and memoirs which may be of considerable interest to researchers.
C. Periodical articles by a variety of authors have been organized in Section C of Series II in order to indicate the types of source material which Bates collected and retained in his files. Some of these articles are readily available elsewhere while others are from fairly obscure journals.
D. Bates spent a great deal of time systematically going through major mission periodicals to dictate notes on items of interest. Comprehensive notes are available in Section D on the China Christian Year Book, China Mission Year Book, China Missionary Bulletin, Chinese Recorder, Educational Review and other periodicals.
E. and F. The notes and references in 3" x 5" and 5 1/2" x 8 1/2" format of Sections E and F have been left in the order in which they were received. Extensive sorting would be required to find material of value among these myriad slips of paper.
Related to organizations
Related to conferences
Topics
Of particular interest are materials related to the Church of Christ in China, the International Missionary Council China Study Group, and the National Christian Council of China.
H. Bates was very much at home with the Chinese language and also employed native Chinese speakers to take notes on Chinese language sources. The value of the notes, bibliographic references and photocopies of Chinese language sources in Section H will need to be determined by someone skilled in the Chinese language.
Series III, "Christian Effort in Chinese Society" Drafts, is in many ways the core of this manuscript group, containing over 3,000 pages of drafts for Bates' proposed book. The drafts include topical drafts that are write-ups of specific subjects, working drafts prepared to coincide with the detailed outline which Bates had developed, and revised working drafts, rewritten to improve their quality and decrease length. These drafts may be of more interest to the informed layperson than to the scholar. They are evaluated elsewhere by the work of Cynthia McLean for the National Council of Churches.
Series IV, Documentation of Prominent Chinese Christians, contains material collected by Bates as part of a project designed to supplement and complement his survey of Christian effort in Chinese society. In the first stage of this project Bates compiled a set of seven lists from various sources documenting Chinese Christians and sent the set to "Select Friends Whose Interest and Cooperation are Trusted". This effort resulted in a set of five revised lists which were broadly distributed to obtain corrections and additional information. Series IV contains full sets of lists from both stages of the project, drafts and notes related to them, and responses from over fifty individuals to whom the lists were sent. The Series concludes with a section of biographical sketches of varying completeness for twenty-seven Chinese Christians.
Series V contains notes and source materials collected by Bates that are not directly related to China. The first two sections of the Series, notes in 3" x 5" and 5 1/2'' x 8 1/2" format, have been left essentially as they were received; some broad topical areas are indicated, but with little recognizable order. A third section of mixed format notes and collected material is somewhat more organized. Of particular interest are documents relating to various aspects of religious liberty. Much of the collected material in this Series will be of little interest to researchers but does serve to illustrate Bates' wide range of interests.
Series VI documents in a very complete way Bates' writings on missions and Third World churches, religious liberty, and a host of other topics. The Series is divided into five sections:
A. Articles, pamphlets, papers
B. Book reviews
C. Reports and memoranda from China
D. Sermons, addresses, interviews
E. Related to major works
The writings in section A date from throughout Bates' career. Not surprisingly, many of them relate to the religious and political situation in China. Bates wrote regularly for periodicals such as Christianity and Crisis and World Call; he contributed articles to various encyclopedias. The book reviews in section B were written by Bates; reviews of his own works are in section E. The reports and memoranda from China are primarily unpublished typescript materials and may be of considerable interest to researchers studying the situation in Nanking, especially during World War II.
The Course Related Materials of Series VII date primarily from Bates' years at Union Theological Seminary where he taught courses on missions, Christian ethics and practical theology. Bates was also a leading force in the Program of Advanced Religious Studies (PARS) at Union.
Other than documents which provide detailed biographical information, much of the material in Series VIII, Personal Items and Memorabilia, is of peripheral interest. It has been retained in order to provide a sense of Bates' personality and interests.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence, 1920-1978, n.d.
II. China Notes and Sources, 1836-1978, n.d.
III. "Christian Effort in Chinese Society" Drafts
IV. Documentation of Prominent Chinese Christians
V. Other Notes and Collected Material, 1928-1978, n.d.
VI. Writings, 1924-1975, n.d.
VII. Course Related Materials, 1942-1965, n.d.
VIII. Personal Items and Memorabilia
Sino-Japanese War, 1894-1895; Missions -- China; Missions; Educators; Missionaries; Bates, M. Searle (Miner Searle), 1897-1978; Jinling da xue; Nanking International Relief Committee; National Christian Council of China; Union Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.); United Board for Christian Higher Education in Asia; United Christian Missionary Society
- Correspondence, Series I
  Scope and Contents
  Series I is divided into three sections:
  Family Correspondence
  China Era Correspondence
  General Correspondence
  The Family Correspondence is arranged chronologically within the following categories:
  1. Miner Searle Bates to/from his wife and sons
  2. MSB and Lilliath Bates to/from mother of MSB
  3. MSB and LB to/from father of MSB
  4. MSB and LB to from siblings of MSB
  5. MSB and LB to/from stepmother of MSB
  6. Correspondence of family members other than Bates
  a. Lilliath Bates (alphabetically arranged)
  b. Miner Lee Bates
  c. Others
  The China Era Correspondence and the General Correspondence are arranged alphabetically by author or recipient other than Bates. Folders labeled with initials only (e.g. "A" or "B-C") are followed by separately labeled folders for notable individuals or organizations.
  - Family Correspondence
    - MSB to/from wife and sons, 1923-1938 (Box 1, Folder 1-13)
    - MSB to/from wife and sons, 1939-1975, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 14-29)
    - MSB and LB to/from mother of MSB, 1920-1921 (Box 2, Folder 30-31)
    - MSB and LB to/from mother of MSB, 1922-1925 (Box 3, Folder 32-35)
    - MSB and LB to/from father of MSB, 1921-1930 (Box 3, Folder 36-39)
    - MSB and LB to/from siblings of MSB, 1929-1978, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 40-42)
    - MSB and LB to/from stepmother of MSB, 1930, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Correspondence of family members
    - Lilliath Bates
      - C - D (Box 3, Folder 44)
      - L- W (Box 3, Folder 45)
      - Christian name only (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - Miner Lee Bates
      - Miner Lee Bates (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - Others
      - Others (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - China Era Correspondence
    - A (Box 4, Folder 49)
    - B - C (Box 4, Folder 50)
    - Bates circular letters, 1927-1950, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 51-53)
    - China International Famine Relief Commission, 1938 (Box 4, Folder 53a)
    - Christian Church (Disciples of Christ), 1920-1950 (Box 4, Folder 54)
    - E - F (Box 4, Folder 55)
    - Fenn, William P. (see also: Gen. corres.), 1949-1950 (Box 4, Folder 56)
    - Foreign Missions Conference of North America - China Committee, 1947-1948, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 57)
    - G - I (Box 4, Folder 58)
    - Haskell, Walter W., 1932 (Box 4, Folder 58)
    - Higdon, E. K. (see: Christian Church - Disciples of Christ) (Box 4, Folder 58)
    - Japanese Embassy, Nanking, 1937-1939 (Box 4, Folder 59)
    - Japanese Embassy, Shanghai, 1938 (Box 4, Folder 59)
    - L (Box 4, Folder 60)
    - Latourette, Kenneth S. (see also: Gen. corres.), 1948 (Box 4, Folder 61)
    - Lobenstine, Edwin C., 1939 (Box 4, Folder 61)
    - Luce, Henry, 1946 (Box 4, Folder 61)
    - M (Box 4, Folder 62)
    - Nanking International Relief Committee, 1941 (Box 4, Folder 63)
    - Nanking, University of; Board of Founders, 1937-1938 (Box 4, Folder 63)
    - National Christian Council, Shanghai, 1938 (Box 4, Folder 63)
    - P - T (Box 4, Folder 64)
    - Virgil (see: Christian Church - Disciples of Christ)
    - Timperley, H. J., 1936-1938 (Box 4, Folder 65)
    - Union Theological Seminary, New York (see: Charles Iglehart)
    - United Board for Christian Colleges in China (see also: Gen. corres.), 1948 (Box 4, Folder 66)
    - United China Relief Christian Missionary Society ( re: Christian Church - Disciples of Christ), 1941 (Box 4, Folder 66)
    - United States Embassy, Nanking, 1938-1940 (Box 4, Folder 67)
    - V - Y (Box 5, Folder 68)
    - Van Dusen, Henry P. (see also: Gen. corres.), 1948-1950 (Box 5, Folder 69)
    - Christian names, anonymous, fragments (Box 5, Folder 70)
  - General Correspondence
    - Ab - Al (Box 5, Folder 71)
    - Am (Box 5, Folder 72)
    - An - Ay (Box 5, Folder 73)
    - The American Oxonian and Rhodes Scholarship Trust, 1965 -1978 (Box 5, Folder 74)
    - Association of Professors of Missions, 1954-1962 (Box 5, Folder 75)
    - Ba (Box 5, Folder 76)
    - Be - Bin (Box 5, Folder 77)
    - Bis - Boh (Box 5, Folder 78)
    - Boy - Bro (Box 5, Folder 79)
    - Bru - By (Box 5, Folder 80)
    - Bates circular letters, 1950-1974 (Box 5, Folder 81)
    - Beach, Robert F. (see: Missionary Research Library, Union Theological Seminary, N.Y.)
    - Beaver, R. Pierce, 1951-1972 (Box 5, Folder 82)
    - Bennett, John C., 1963-1969 (Box 5, Folder 82)
    - Bingle, Ernest J. (see: International Missionary Council; re. China Study)
    - Boorman, Howard L., 1968-1971, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 83)
    - Boynton, Charles L., 1961-1964 (Box 5, Folder 84)
    - Brown, Margaret H., 1951-1972 (Box 5, Folder 85)
    - Ca (Box 6, Folder 86)
    - Cha (Box 6, Folder 87)
    - Che (Box 6, Folder 88)
    - Chi - Chu (Box 6, Folder 89)
    - Cl (Box 6, Folder 90)
    - Col (Box 6, Folder 91)
    - Com - Coo (Box 6, Folder 92)
    - Cor - Cr (Box 6, Folder 93)
    - Chen, Theodore H. E., 1967-1968 (Box 6, Folder 94)
    - China Records Project (see also: Yale Divinity School Library), 1968-1973 (Box 6, Folder 96)
    - Cho, Kiyoko T., 1968-1977 (Box 6, Folder 97)
    - Christian Church (Disciples of Christ), 1950-1969, 1970-1977, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 98, 99)
    - Copland, E. Bruce, 1953-1968 (Box 6, Folder 100)
    - D (Box 6, Folder 101)
    - Decker, John W. (see also: International Missionary Council; re. China Study), 1950-1974 (Box 6, Folder 102)
    - Ea - El (Box 6, Folder 103)
    - En - Ev (Box 6, Folder 104)
    - Fa - Fi (Box 6, Folder 105)
    - Fl - Fu (Box 6, Folder 106)
    - Fairbank, John K., 1966-1973 (Box 6, Folder 107)
    - Fenn, William P. (see also: China era corres.), 1953-1975 (Box 7, Folder 108)
    - Ga - Gl (Box 7, Folder 109)
    - Go - Gu (Box 7, Folder 110)
    - Hai - Har (Box 7, Folder 111)
    - Haw - He (Box 7, Folder 112)
    - Hi (Box 7, Folder 113)
    - Ho - Hol (Box 7, Folder 114)
    - Hoo - Hs (Box 7, Folder 115)
    - Hu - Hy (Box 7, Folder 116)
    - Harr, Wilbur C. (see: Association of Professors of Missions)
    - Hyslop, Ralph D., 1954-1963 (Box 7, Folder 117)
    - I (Box 7, Folder 118)
    - International Missionary Council: General (see also: China era corres.), 1950 (Box 7, Folder 119)
    - International Missionary Council: Re. China Study Project, 1954-1955 Feb (Box 7, Folder 120)
    - International Missionary Council: Re. China Study Project, 1955-1956, 1967, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 121-124)
    - J (Box 7, Folder 125)
    - Jones, Francis P., 1961-1975 (Box 7, Folder 126)
    - K (Box 7, Folder 127)
    - Keeny, Spurgeon M., 1955-1976 (Box 7, Folder 128)
    - La - Li (Box 7, Folder 129)
    - Lo (Box 7, Folder 130)
    - Lu - Ly (Box 8, Folder 131)
    - Lacy, Creighton (see also: International Missionary Council; re. China Study), 1955-1972 (Box 8, Folder 132)
    - Latourette, Kenneth S. (see also: China era corres.), 1935-1955 (Box 8, Folder 133)
    - Ma - McG (Box 8, Folder 134)
    - Macm - Mat (Box 8, Folder 135)
    - Mc (Box 8, Folder 136)
    - Mi (Box 8, Folder 137)
    - Mo - My (Box 8, Folder 138)
    - MacInnis, Donald, 1967-1973 (Box 8, Folder 139)
    - Maloy, Robert M. (see: Missionary Research Library, Union Theological Seminary, N.Y.), 1974-1978, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 140)
    - Maryknoll Publications (Box 8, Folder 141)
    - Merwin, Wallace C. (see also: International Missionary Council; re. China Study), 1955-1968 (Box 8, Folder 142)
    - Merwin, Wallace C., 1970-1978 (Box 8, Folder 143)
    - Missionary Research Library,Union Theological Seminary, N.Y., 1951-1978 (Box 8, Folder 144-148)
    - Na (Box 8, Folder 149)
    - Ne - No (Box 8, Folder 150)
    - National Council of Churches of Christ in the U.S.A.: Department of Education for Mission (Friendship Press), 1967-1969 (Box 9, Folder 151)
    - National Council of Churches of Christ in the U.S.A.: Department of Religious Liberty, 1953-1956 (Box 9, Folder 152)
    - National Council of Churches of Christ in the U.S.A.: Division of Foreign Missions - Africa Committee, 1955 (Box 9, Folder 153)
    - National Council of Churches of Christ in the U.S.A.: Division of Foreign Missions - Africa Committee, 1956-1961 (Box 9, Folder 154)
    - Nielson, Erik W. (see: International Missionary Council; re. China Study)
    - O (Box 9, Folder 155)
    - Pa (Box 9, Folder 156)
    - Pe - Po (Box 9, Folder 157)
    - Pr - Pu (Box 9, Folder 158)
    - Ra - Rh (Box 9, Folder 159)
    - Ri - Rom (Box 9, Folder 160)
    - Roo - Ru (Box 9, Folder 161)
    - Rabe, Valentin, 1970-1978 (Box 9, Folder 162)
    - Richardson, William (see: Maryknoll Publications)
    - Sa - Sc (Box 9, Folder 163)
    - Se - She (Box 9, Folder 164)
    - Shi - Si (Box 9, Folder 165)
    - Sm (Box 9, Folder 166)
    - So (Box 9, Folder 167)
    - Sp - Ste (Box 9, Folder 168)
    - Sto - Sw (Box 9, Folder 169)
    - Sailer, Randolph C., 1977, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 170)
    - Smith, Joseph M. (see: Christian Church - Disciples of Christ)
    - Social Science Research Council, 1959-1967 (Box 9, Folder 171)
    - Ta - Th (Box 9, Folder 172)
    - Ti - Ty (Box 9, Folder 173)
    - Teng, S. Y., 1951-1952 (Box 10, Folder 174)
    - Theological Education Fund, 1962-1975 (Box 10, Folder 175)